Montgomery Dent Corse Papers, 1846-1982
Alexandria Library, Local History/Special Collections
Alexandria Library, Local History/Special Collections
Montgomery Dent Corse Papers, 1846-1982
Alexandria Library, Local History/Special Collections
65
1 box (0.5 linear feet)
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
There are no restrictions.
Acquisition Information
Donated by grandson of Montgomery D. Corse, Thomas S. Corse, of San Diego, California, December 1981.
Alternative Form Available
Xerox copies of the letters are located with the originals in Box 65.
Biographical/Historical Information
Montgomery Dent Corse (1816-1895) was born at Alexandria, Virginia on March 14, 1816, the eldest son of John and Julia Corse. He attended Major Bradley Lowe's military school and Benjamin Hallowell's school on Washington Street. As a young boy he witnessed Lafayette's 1825 visit to Alexandria and participated in the inauguration of President Jackson in 1829.
In 1846, Corse mustered a company of volunteers for service in Mexico, serving as their captain. He sailed for California in 1849 and participated in gold mining. Although he made a short visit to Alexandria in 1855, he did not permanently return until December 1856. Thereafter, he was employed in the banking business of his brothers.
Corse served as 1st lieutenant of the Alexandria Home Guard in 1859 and was elected captain of the Old Dominion Rifles on January 7, 1861. He eventually was commissioned as colonel of the 17th Virginia Regiment, taking part in the major battles of the Army of Northern Virginia. He was wounded at Second Manassas, South Mountain, and Antietam. Promoted brigadier general after Antietam, Corse's brigade was on detached service in the Blackwater River area southeast of Petersburg. After attempting to retake New Bern, NC, the brigade returned to Howlett's Line, between Petersburg and Richmond, where he was wounded for the fourth time. At the battle of Saylor's Creek, Corse was captured and held prisoner-of-war at Fort Warren, Boston, Massachusetts until July 24, 1865.
He returned to Alexandria and went into a trading business with his brother. He was a charter member of the R.E. Lee Camp, United Confederate Veterans, and on May 24, 1880 was a distinguished guest along with Governor Fitzhugh Lee and General Joseph E. Johnson, at the dedication of the Confederate monument at Washington and Prince Streets. He died on February 11, 1895.
Corse married Elizabeth Beverley (1825-1894) on November 22, 1862. They had four children: Virginia Beverley Corse (1863 or 1864-1919), Montgomery Beverley Corse (1866-1931), William Beverley Corse (1867-1911), and Elizabeth Beverley Corse (1871-1933).
Scope and Content
The bulk of the collection is related to Montgomery D. Corse's military career, including muster rolls, commission and discharge certificates, and 63 letters written by Corse to his wife, Elizabeth Beverley Corse, during his participation in the Civil War. In addition, the papers of Midshipman William H. Peters and a few letters written by Mrs. Corse are included.
Arrangement
Letters, certificates, and additional papers of Montgomery Dent Corse are filed chronologically and by related topics, the Mexican War and the Civil War. Midshipman William Peter's papers are organized chronologically within folder #14, followed by the xerox copies of related photographs.
Adjunct Descriptive Data
Related Material
Vertical file: Biographical Material - Corse, Montgomery Dent, including a biography written by Corse's grandson. See also Hurd, William B., Montgomery Dent Corse, Alexandria History. Allan W. Robbins, Ed. Alexandria, VA: Alexandria Historical Society, 1982.
Index Terms
Alexandria (Va.)--History--Civil War, 1861-1865; Confederate States of America. Army. Virginia Infantry Regiment, 17th.; Corse, Elizabeth Beverley, 1825-1894; Corse, Montgomery Dent, 1816-1895
Contents List
- Four Muster Rolls: 1st Virginia Volunteers; original Muster Roll of the Proclamation of the Virginia Governor establishing the Virginia Volunteers (Mexican War, 1846); List of the 1st Volunteers. (Box-folder 65:1)
- Montgomery D. Corse: Commission as Captain, Company B, First Regiment of Virginia Volunteer Infantry, December 26, 1846; Discharge from duty, First Regiment of Virginia Volunteer Infantry, August 1848. (Box-folder 65:2)
- Montgomery D. Corse: Commissioned colonel of Virginia Active Volunteer Forces, May 17, 1861. Orders to Report to Duty, May 21, 1861; Muster Roll, Company F, 17th Regiment, Virginia Volunteers, June 30-August 31, 1861. (Box-folder 65:3)
- Letters, Montgomery D. Corse to Elizabeth B. Corse, March 26 - November 14, 1863. (Box-folder 65:4)
- Letters, Montgomery D. Corse to Elizabeth B. Corse, January 20 - June 24, 1864. (Box-folder 65:5)
- Letters, Montgomery D. Corse to Elizabeth B. Corse, July 7 - December 29, 1864. (Box-folder 65:6)
- Letters, Montgomery D. Corse to Elizabeth B. Corse, January 2 - August 29, 1865. (Box-folder 65:7)
- Xerox Copies of Letters, Montgomery D. Corse to Elizabeth B. Corse, March 26 - November 14, 1863. (Box-folder 65:8)
- Xerox Copies of Letters, Montgomery D. Corse to Elizabeth B. Corse, January 20 - December 29, 1864. (Box-folder 65:9)
- Xerox Copies of Letters, Montgomery D. Corse to Elizabeth B. Corse, January 2 - August 29, 1865. (Box-folder 65:10)
- Montgomery D. Corse: Oath of Allegiance to the United States, Fort Warren, Boston, Massachusetts, July 24, 1865; Duplicate copy in writing. (Box-folder 65:11)
- Montgomery D. Corse: Department of the Interior, Bureau of Pensions, Mexican War Survivors Pension Certificate, May 14, 1887. (Box-folder 65:12)
- Letters to Mrs. Corse (Elizabeth Beverley) from her brother, William Beverley, November 4, 1865, June 29, 1857; from Mary Custis Lee, 1863 or 1864. (Box-folder 65:13)
- Midshipman William H. Peters Papers: Correspondence, April 12, 1825 - May 15, 1827; David Peter Family: Petition in the Case of Martha Dick and others, March 1853. (Box-folder 65:14)
- Xerox copies of photographs: Mary Custis Lee, April 1858; Montgomery D. Corse and John D. Corse, bankers; Thomas S. Corse, May 26, 1985. (Box-folder 65:15)
- Correspondence: Includes information on Corse Family and donation of the Corse Family papers by Thomas Semmes Corse and Allison Corse Semmes, 1981-1982. (Box-folder 65:16)